Patent medicine almanacs
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Original collection, 1843-1966; Series I
  - National Calendar or Herrick's Almanac, 1885, 1886, 1887, 1888, 1889 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Published by the proprietors of Dr. Herrick's Family Medicines, New York, N.Y. Another 1888 almanac has been cataloged separately under National calendar, or Herrick's almanac.
  - National Calendar or Herrick's Almanac, 1890, 1891, 1892, 1893, 1894 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Published by the Proprietors of Dr. Herrick's Family Medicines, New York, N.Y.
  - National Calendar or Herrick's Almanac, 1896, 1900, 1902, 1903, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Published by the Proprietors of Dr. Herrick's Family Medicines, New York, N.Y. The 1911 almanac was published by Dr. Herrick's Family Medicine Co., James F. Ballard, proprietor, St. Louis, Mo.
  - The National State Almanac, 1884, 1886 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Published by Wells, Richardson & Co., Burlington, Vt. See also the Vermont State Almanac.
  - The New-England Almanac and Farmer's Friend, 1861, 1863, 1864, 1865 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Published by Starr & Co., New London, Conn. 1864 and 1865 almanacs published by C. Prince (Starr & Co.), New London, Conn.
  - The New England Almanac and Farmer's Friend, 1866, 1867, 1869, 1870 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Published by C. Prince, New London, Conn.
  - New-England Farmer's Almanac, 1856 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    By Truman W. Abell (Dr. Truman Abell's New England Family Medicines). Published by Jones & Cogswell, Concord, N.H.
  - The New York Almanac, 1888, 1901, 1903 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Published by the Centaur Company, New York, N.Y.
  - Northrop & Lyman Co.'s Almanac, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Published by Northrop & Lyman Co. Limited, Toronto, Canada.
  - Pain-Killer Almanac & Family Receipt Book, 1867, 1868 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Published by Perry Davis & Son, Providence, R.I.
  - Parke & Parke Limited Almanac, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Published by Parke & Parke Limited, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada.
  - The People's Almanac, 1855 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Published by Louden & Co., Druggists and Chemists, Philadelphia.
  - The People's Almanac, 1855 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Published by Bennett & Beers, Richmond, Va.
  - The People's Illustrated Almanac, 1850 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Published by Clapp & Townsend, New York, N.Y.
  - The Peruna Almanac, 1901, 1902, 1903, 1906, 1916, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Published by the Peruna Drug Manufacturing Co., Columbus, Ohio. The almanacs for 1916 and 1918 were published by the Peruna Co., Columbus, Ohio.
  - Piso's Pocket Book Almanac, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Miniature almanac 5x3 cm. published by the Piso Company, Warren, Pa.
  - Poor Richard's Lactopeptine Almanack, 1914 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Published by the New York Pharmacal Association, Yonkers, N.Y.
  - Rawleigh's Almanac, 1911, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Published by the W.T. Rawleigh Medical Company, Freeport, Ill. The 1911 almanac is titled Rawleigh's Almanac Cook Book & Medical Guide, and the 1923 almanac is titled Rawleigh's Good Health Guide Almanac Cook Book.
  - Der Recept-Kalender, 1875 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Published by David D. Elder & Co., Philadelphia. This almanac is more of a popular health manual than an advertisement for patent medicines.
  - Rescue of Tula Almanac, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Published by B. L. Judson & Co., New York, N.Y. Indian motif.
  - Rosdalis Almanac, 1870, 1873 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Published by Clements & Co., Baltimore, Md.
  - Rush's Almanac and Guide to Health, 1869 (2 versions), 1873, 1877, 1878, 1879, 1880 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Published by Dr. A. H. Flanders, New York, N.Y.
  - Scheetz's Illustrated Almanac, 1872 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Published by Jacob Scheetz, Philadelphia.
  - Schenck's Almanac, 1868, 1869, 1870, 1873, 1878 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    Published by Dr. J. H. Schenck, Philadelphia. Almanacs for 1873 and 1878 were published by Dr. J. H. Schenck & Son, Philadelphia.
  - Schenck's Almanach, 1874 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Seven Barks Almanac, 1885, 1886 (2 versions), 1892 (2 versions) (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Published by Lyman Brown, New York, N.Y. Almanac for 1885 is titled Seven Barks. Almanac for 1886 is titled the 7 Wonders of the World Almanac.
  - Shaker Almanac, 1882, 1884, 1885, 1886, 1892 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Published by A. J. White, New York, N.Y. The 1882 almanac is titled The Story of the Shakers...Calendar.
  - Swamp Root Almanac, 1911, 1913, 1942, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Published by Dr. Kilmer & Co., Binghamton, N.Y. The 1943 almanac was published by Kilmer & Co., Inc., Stamford, Conn. Indian motif on cover.
  - Trail Blazer's Almanac, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Published by Trail Blazer's Pub. Co., Kewanee, Ill. Advertises a wide variety of merchandise besides medicines.
  - Treasure Chest Almanac, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Published by Dr. Pierce's Clinic, Buffalo, N.Y.
  - Tucker & Co.'s National Almanac, 1858, 1859 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Published by M. H. Tucker & Co., successors to George W. Merchant, Lockport, N.Y. See also the Gargling Oil Company's National Almanac, and Merchant's Gargling Oil Almanac.
  - University Almanac and Business Book, 1869, 1871, 1872, 1876 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Published by the University Publishing Society, New York, N.Y. The company was located on University Place in New York and claimed to be related to the New York Medical University.
  - Vennor's Weather Almanac, 1883 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Published by A. Vogeler & Co., Baltimore, Md.
  - The Vermont State Almanac, 1883, 1884, 1885 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Published by Wells, Richardson & Co., Burlington, Vt. See also the National State Almanac. Another issue under the title Vermont State Almanac (published in 1884), has been cataloged separately.
  - Veterans of the War...Almanac, 1869 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Paid for by H. T. Helmbold, New York and Philadelphia. Includes "History of the Late Rebellion, from 1860 to 1865," published by the Soldiers & Sailors' Publishing Company.
  - Vinegar Bitters Almanac, 1872, 1873, 1874, 1878, 1879 (2 versions) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Published by R. H. McDonald & Co., Druggists and General Agents, San Francisco, California. One 1879 almanac has an advertisement on the back cover for E. A. Gessner, Dealers in Drugs, Medicines & Chemicals...New Haven, Conn.
  - Warner's Safe Cure Almanac, 1892 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Published by H. H. Warner & Co., Rochester, N.Y. Another issue under the title Warner's Safe Calendar, 1884-5 has been cataloged separately.
  - Watkins Almanac, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Published by the J. R. Watkins Medical Company, Winona, Minn.
  - Wright's Pictorial Family Almanac, 1851, 1853, 1854, 1855 (2 versions) (Box 10, Folder 11)
    Published by Dr. Wm. Wright, Philadelphia. The 1851 almanac is titled Wright's Family Almanac. After 1851, there is an Indian scene on the bottom of the cover.
  - Wright's Pictorial Family Almanac, 1858, 1859, 1862, 1863, 1865 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Wright's Pictorial Family Almanac, 1866, 1869, 1887, 1890, 1892, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Later almanacs published by E. Ferrett, Agent for Wright's Indian Vegetable Pills, New York, N.Y.
- Supplement from the collection of Lloyd Moore, 1867-1932; Series II
  Scope and Contents
  These almanacs, housed in three notebooks, were collected by Professor Lloyd Moore (1916-2004). Moore was a graduate of Columbia University (1939) and the Brooklyn College of Pharmacy (1944). He was an active member of the American Pharmaceutical Association. His collection of almanacs and other medical ephemera was used as part of his lectures at the Brooklyn College of Pharmacy and Nassau Community College.
  - Hostetter's Illustrated United States Almanac, 1867-1899 (Volume 1)
    Full title is Hostetter's Illustrated United States Almanac for Merchants, Mechanics, Miners, Farmers, Planters and General Family Use. This volume contains a complete set of almanacs from 1867 through 1899. Published by Hostetter & Smith, Pittsburgh through 1885. Published by Hostetter & Co., Pittsburgh, 1886-1890. Published by the Hostetter Company, Pittsburgh, 1891-1899. The main product advertised was Hostetter's Stomach Bitters.
  - Hostetter's Illustrated Unites States Almanac, 1900-1910 (Volume 2)
    Complete set of almanacs from 1900 to 1910, published by the Hostetter Company, Pittsburgh, Pa.
  - Other patent medicine almanacs, 1876-1932 (Volume 3)
    Items maintained in the order established by the collector, Professor Moore, who created an index to them.
    - Green's Diary Almanac, 1882 (Volume 3, Item 1)
      Published by G. G. Green, Woodbury, New Jersey. Advertises Boschee's German Syrup, Green's August Flower, and Green's Ague Conqueror.
    - Green's Atlas and Diary Almanac, 1881 (Volume 3, Item 2)
    - Barker's Illustrated Almanac, 1897 (Volume 3, Item 3)
      Published by the Barker, Moore & Mein Medicine Company, Philadelphia. Advertises Barker's Nerve and Bone Liniment and Barker's Horse, Cattle & Poultry Powder.
    - Merchant's Gargling Oil Almanac, 1879 (Volume 3, Item 4)
      Published by Merchant's Gargling Oil Company, Lockport, New York. Advertises Merchant's Gargling Oil Liniment, "a liniment for man and beast."
    - Mrs. Winslow's Domestic Receipt Book, 1876 (Volume 3, Item 5)
      Published by Jeremiah Curtis & Sons, Boston, and John I. Brown & Sons, New York. Advertises Mrs. Winslow's Soothing Syrup, a remedy for infants that contained opium; Brown's Bronchial Troches, Brown's Vermifuge Confits, Brown's Household Panacea, and Brown's Camphorated Saponaceous Dentifrice. The pamphlet contains recipes for meals and for household use.
    - Doan's Directory of the United States, 1909 (Volume 3, Item 6)
      Published by the Foster-Milburn Co., Buffalo, New York. The Directory lists the population of every town in the United States with over 1000 people. The pamphlet advertises Doan's Kidney Pills and other medications.
    - Doan's Directory of the U.S. with Latest Census of Large Cities, 1913-1914 (Volume 3, Item 7)
    - Doan's Directory of the Unites States, Latest Edition, 1926 (Volume 3, Item 8)
      Advertises Doan's Pills, "stimulant diuretic to the kidneys," and other medications.
    - Doan's Directory of the United States, Latest Edition, 1932 (Volume 3, Item 9)
    - Dr. D. Jayne's Medical Almanac and Guide to Health, 1888 (Volume 3, Item 10)
      Published by Dr. D. Jayne & Son, Philadelphia. Advertises Dr. D. Jayne's Family Medicines including Expectorant, Tonic Vermifuge, Specific for Tape Worm, Carminative Balsam, Alterative, Liniment or Counter Irritant, Sanative Pills, and Hair Tonic.
    - Vinegar Bitters Almanac: Devoted to Temperance, Health and Economy, 1874 (Volume 3, Item 11)
      Published by R. H. McDonald & Co., Druggists and General Agents, San Francisco. Advertises Dr. Walker's California Vinegar Bitters, the "only temperance bitters known."
    - National Calendar or Herrick's Almanac, 1891 (Volume 3, Item 12)
      "Published by the Proprietors of Dr. Herrick's Family Medicine," New York. Advertises Herrick's Sugar-Coated Vegetable Liver Pills, Renne's Pain-Killing Magic Oil, Dr. Herrick's German Horse Liniment, Harvell's Condition Powders (also veterinary), and various Herrick's plasters.
    - National Calendar or Herrick's Almanac, 1902 (Volume 3, Item 13)
    - Burdock Blood Bitters Almanac and Key to Health, 1889 (Volume 3, Item 14)
      Published by Foster, Milburn & Co., Buffalo, New York. Advertises Burdock Blood Bitters (B.B.B.) and Dr. Thomas' Electric Oil.
    - Pierce's Memorandum Account Book, 1881 (Volume 3, Item 15)
      Published by the World's Dispensary Medical Association, Buffalo, New York. Advertises Dr. Pierce's Standard Medicines. Pierce is Dr. R. V. Pierce.
    - Epilepsy (Fits) and St. Vitus's Dance (Chorea). World Dispensary Dime Series, 1885 (Volume 3, Item 16)
      R. V. Pierce, M.D. was consulting physician to the Invalids' Hotel and Surgical Institute, Buffalo, New York. This publication advertises the institution and its successful cases.